<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

	<properties>
		<title>NeuClear Ledger API</title>
		<author email="pelle@neubia.com">Pelle Braendgaard</author>
	</properties>

	<body>
        <section name="Major upcoming release of NeuClear Ledger API - Release 0.3">
            <p>
                [August 4th, 2003]
                Major new release is in the works. It is mostly workable in CVS at the moment, but needs
                some cleaning up and improved documentation. Major new features:

            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>SQL Database support</li>
                <li>Improved model of HeldTransactions now seperated out from actual ledger.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="New Release of NeuClear Ledger API - Release 0.2">
            <p>
                [January 26th, 2003] New Release Available. New Release contains a working implementation using Java Collections API.
                Several changes to the API including 2 distinct Transaction classes. Also much improved documentation.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="New Busy Developer Guide to the NeuClear API" href="/bdg.html">
            <p>
                [January 26th, 2003] New improved documentation includes a Busy Developer Guide to get developers started quickly.
            </p>
        </section>
		<section name="Introduction">
			<p>
                Many applications in business need access to a double entry ledger. This could be a General Ledger for a company
                or an account system in a bank. NeuClear as a framework for creating financial clearing system needed a standardized api
                for integrating with existing ledgers or creating new ledgers.
            </p>
            <p>
                The API is very simple and it should be very easy to implement it. Everything has been written with security in mind. This
                is not to say that it is secure, as it hasn't been properly reviewed. Reviews should also take the underlying implementations into account.
            </p>
		</section>
        <section name="Features">
            <p>The following is what the main feature list is:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Backend plugins to support legacy and new Ledgers
                </li>
                <li>Account Scheme plugins to support different account naming schemes, such as bank accounts, neudist, charts of accounts etc.</li>
                <li>Small and secure</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
	</body>

</document>
